<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copy of two  letters sent from Spaine containing the Kings censure for the rooting out of vices, abuses, and all sorts of briberies and corruptions in his kingdomes.</title>
            <author>Spain. Sovereign (1621-1665 : Philip IV)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09562</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19843.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23935019</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23935019</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26986</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09562)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26986)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1838:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copy of two  letters sent from Spaine containing the Kings censure for the rooting out of vices, abuses, and all sorts of briberies and corruptions in his kingdomes.</title>
                  <author>Spain. Sovereign (1621-1665 : Philip IV)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.K. for William Lee, and are to bee sold  at his shop in Fleetstreete, at the Golden Bucke, neere Serieants Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First letter signed: Yo el Rey.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴(-A1) B⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spain --  History --  Philip IV, 1621-1665.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26986:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
            <p>THE COPY OF TWO LETTERS SENT FROM <hi>SPAINE:</hi> CONTAINING <hi>The Kings Cenſure for the rooting out</hi> of Vices, Abuſes, and all ſorts of Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries and corruptions in his <hi>Kingdomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>F K</head>
               <q>PAX OPVLENTIAM. SAPENTIA PACEM.</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by F.K. for <hi>William Lee,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in Fleetſtreete, <hi>at the golden Bucke, neere Serieants Inne.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26986:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26986:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
            <head>The Copy of the firſt Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering the great Obligation that lies vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, in that God hath put vpon my ſhoulders the adminiſtration and gouernment of ſo many Kingdomes and Dominions, with the name and ſtile of Catholike King; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto appertaineth an ardent zeale and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the publike good: And that the things which augment theſe Obligations, are the examples of Chriſtian piety, which did ſhine ſo gloriouſly in the King, my Lord and Father (who is now in glory:) as likewiſe that notable care and diligence in gouernment, together with the ſeuere diſcipline of the King my Father, and my Grandfather: I am reſolued to ſettle a kind of cenſure for the rooting out of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26986:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->vices, abuſes, and all ſorts of bribery and corruption in theſe my Kingdomes. And to this end, I ordaine and command you, our Preſident, that you firme and order a <hi>Junta,</hi> or <hi>Committee,</hi> of theſe perſons fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: of whoſe vertue and zeale I haue a particular truſt and confidence.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Maeſtro Fray Antonio de Soto</hi> Mayor, my Confeſſor.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Don Franciſco de Contreras,</hi> of my Councell.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Don Pedro Porto Carrero,</hi> Conde of <hi>Medelin,</hi> of all other the ancienteſt, Mayor-domo, or Chamberlaine of my Lord the King.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Don Franciſco de Riuera,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Malpica,</hi> a Gentleman of the Chamber of my Father and Grandfather.</item>
               <item>5. <hi>Don Diego de Corral,</hi> of my Councell.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Don Franciſco de Seiada,</hi> of my Councell.</item>
               <item>7. Father <hi>Hieronymo de Florentia,</hi> my Preacher, or Chaplaine, and Confeſſor of the moſt Illuſtrious Infanta's my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</item>
               <item>8. Frier <hi>Juan de Peralta,</hi> Prior of Saint
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26986:3"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 66 -->
                  <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> and Lord Elect of <hi>Tuy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. Doctor <hi>Aluaro de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illegas,</hi> Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Arch-biſhopricke of <hi>Toledo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10. And for Secretary, <hi>Pedro de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treras.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And this <hi>Iunta</hi> or meeting, is to be made in your preſence, when your great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments ſhall not hinder you; and your Seſſions ſhall be euery Sunday, for ſo holy a day ought not to bee a hinderance to ſo holy a worke and Chriſtian action. And if you ſhall thinke it fit, you may appoint ſome other day in the weeke: And the firſt Seſſion ſhall be the firſt Thurſday after Eaſter: And you ſhall giue entrance to this worke with a Benediction or thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing to God, deſiring him (by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion of his bleſſed Mother) to indue me with his grace, and to giue ſupply to my tender yeeres, that I may hit the marke aright, and gouerne my ſelfe according to his holy Law, and to the generall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and publike good of all my Kingdoms and Dominions. And that this beginning, being giuen to ſo diuine a Seruice, may the better proceed in ordering the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26986:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->of State, of Warre, of my Treaſurie, which requires ſuch a deale of care and vigilancy.</p>
            <p>As for any inſtructions to be giuen to this <hi>Junta,</hi> or Seſsion of yours, it ſeemeth to me that it cannot be committed to any better then the <hi>Committee</hi> it ſelfe: And therefore your firſt Seſsion ſhall be to this effect:</p>
            <p>To frame your Inſtructions in the beſt manner you can deuiſe, and to ſend the ſame vnto me, that I may peruſe them, and that I may ſend you them backe againe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed with my hand for your ſecond Seſsion. <hi>Yo el Rey.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:26986:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 67 -->
            <head>The Copy of the ſecond Letter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince I wrote by the laſt Poſt, another Hiſtorie may bee made of the changes and alterations of this Court: From the late Kings Confeſſor they haue taken all his Offices, and quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him of his rent, which was a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue, amounting to more then 30000. Ducats: Being, beſides, commanded to leaue the Court, and to retire himſelfe to a Monaſtery of his owne Order, ſome 20. leagues diſtant from the Court. As ſoone as he was gone out of <hi>Madrid,</hi> they ſeized vpon all that he had; And iourneying vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the way, there were certain Officers ſet of purpoſe to regiſter what hee carried with him, and to ſtrip him of all ſaue his apparell and what was needfull for his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26986:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->iourney. The ſelfe-ſame day they bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the Duke of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zeda,</hi> and laid hands on his Secretarie, and likewiſe quitted all his ſeruants and officers from the Palace, which had been placed there by the Duke of <hi>Lerma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, his Maieſtie publiſhed a Decree or Schedule, giuing commiſsion to <hi>Don Fernando Carillo,</hi> and other Iudges, for examining of all thoſe Mercedes or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, which the deceaſed King had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> his ſonnes and ſeruants, to ſee if there were iuſt cauſe, and reaſon ſufficient for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing the ſaid fauours, and in caſe that they ſhould not find it to bee ſo, then to proceed according to Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Touching the buſineſſe of the Duke of <hi>Oſſuna,</hi> there is no good blood in it, it is all very foule; for they haue laid to his charge the vildeſt and moſt enormous things that euer were heard of, and they haue clapt him vp in priſon, with a very ſtrong gard vpon him, and his buſineſſe (as all the reſt of the like nature) is to bee weighed in the ballance of Iuſtice: for the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26986:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 68 -->King hath a purpoſe to repaire the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of this Monarchy, which was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to run to ruine, for want of executing Iuſtice (which is the prop of eſtates.) <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deron</hi> had beene once more put to the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if hee had not freely confeſſed all, which they were willing to worke out of him; Hee himſelfe wrote his owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, containing ſeuen ſheetes of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. It is thought, ere it be long, that they will make a riddance of all thoſe that were the Dukes followers, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, of thoſe that were his houſhold ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants <hi>(eodem pane &amp; aqua viuentes)</hi> that had eaten of his bread, and dranke of his drinke: to ſo bad a paſſe is the promotion of the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> now come, <hi>that it is great pitie to ſee how deiectedly they walke vp and downe, like men that are troden vnder foot, neuer to riſe againe.</hi> His Maieſtie hath nominated a <hi>Committee,</hi> for the reforming of all the diſorders and euill cuſtomes of the Court, and once a weeke they meete for the ordering of what is requiſite in this kind: and that buſineſſe is ſo farre ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced, that they are come to a repartiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26986:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->or diuiding of all the ſtreets in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> betweene the <hi>Alcaldes,</hi> who goe from houſe to houſe, to know what people lodge therein, and what their buſineſſe is.</p>
            <p>Father <hi>Florentia</hi> is of this <hi>Junta</hi> or <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee,</hi> and carries a great hand, not onely in this, but in all things elſe, and the King is well pleaſed with his counſell and aduice: It is now well knowne that he is Confeſſor to the two Infanta's, <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The people are generally well conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the new King, and the ſpirit and mettle which he ſhewes, and hee leaneth very much to holy and exemplary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in the conferring of Offices, remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thoſe from them which are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe inclined: He hath quitted the abuſe of the Palace, and of the whole Court, of riſing at twelue at noone, and dining at three; riſing himſelfe at ſixe, and giuing audience very early; dining at twelue, and ſupping at eight. It is a thing to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at, to ſee how conuerſant hee is in buſineſſe, as likewiſe to conſider the wiſe and diſcreet anſweres that come from him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26986:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 69 -->
On Tueſday laſt the Kings Funerals were ſolemnized in the Monaſterie of S. <hi>Jeronymo,</hi> whither he had withdrawne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſince the deceaſe of his Father. <hi>Padre Florentia</hi> (as his manner is) made a moſt excellent Sermon: The Tombe was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſumptuous, and coſt many Ducats, and there were 3000. lights and torches: At the Maſſe, there aſsiſted aboue twentie Biſhops, and many other Grandes were in that ſolemnitie, very worthy and ſeeming, and too long the recounting.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here came now newes hither to <hi>Madrid,</hi> of a very diſaſterous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which happened at <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nado,</hi> vpon Saint <hi>James</hi> his day laſt; for they, hauing deferred the proclaiming of the new King vntill then, the more to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnize it vpon their Patrons Feaſt day, there was ſuch a number of people gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, that in their Market-place, a new houſe, being ouercharged with peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (that came to ſee the ſight) fell downe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26986:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->and killed to the number of 300. perſons, being all, or for the moſt part, women; and maimed and lamed neere as many more. This we receiued from an Engliſh Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that liues there, that was a ſpectator of this lamentable chance.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:26986:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 70 -->
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
